

# Sergei Shilko

Creativity is intelligence having fun - Albert Einstein



Berlin, 12627



contact@sshilko.com



https://sshilko.com



English, German







## BACKGROUND



#### **ABOUT**

I'm engineer with hands-on experience in backends, REST & RPC APIs, AWS cloud certified. Skilled with online social networks, realtime chat, video call, online booking, accounting & billing, search, online payments, fraud & risk systems. Proficient with Docker, AWS, PHP, Golang.



### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

 Senior Software Engineer - Billing & Accounting, Foundations (Go, K8s, AWS, GCP, PHP8) www.messagebird.com Jun, 2022 - Present

Working on foundation services built with Go, K8s, PHP, AWS, GCP: accounts, accounting, billing, payments.

- REST APIs, OpenAPI v3, Google GRPC & protobuf APIs both in PHP8 and Golang 1.20
- Backend apps for message delivery over different channels: SMS, MMS, Voice, WhatsApp, Viber...
- Microservice architecture, platform services, product services, IaC, event bus, api-first, domain-driven design
- o Customer UI portal improvements to authentication: adopt JWT tokens, reworked containers startup/shutdown, unit-test coverage
- o Define and adopt SLO, SLI, alerting with Prometheus, Thanos & Graphana dashboards
- CP Billing & Accounting runtime with >5000 RPS billing OLTP workers high load async billing
- Optimized high-load billing k8s cluster runtime performance, resulted in 60% cost reduction: opencensus, lightstep, jaeger
- Optimized speed of Gitlab CI/CD pipelines for K8s deployments: gitlab, docker, k8s, helm
- MEP billing, accounting, invoicing, pricing, quoting features in globally distributed multi-region app: golang/echo.v4, dynamodb/single-table
- Accounting security features like 2FA, SSO, reCaptcha, rate-limiting ...
- CPQ Quoting and Pricing project: set of APIs for self-serve application for creating custom enterprise sales offers

Head of Engineering at Tandem Language Exchange App www.tandem.net,

Leaderhip and hands-on role, 1M DAU, 12+ Engineers, 50+ employees, education domain. Microservices applications, grow & manage team, analytics, business continuity. Building and running software at scale.

Scaled backend infrastructure from 1000 RPM to 80000 RPM, from 100kDAU to >1mDAU and <50ms API</li>

- response time
- Scaled backend capacity from 1000's of users to >15M users
- Applied cost savings plans and utilized AWS Spot instances to reduce costs by 32%
- Hired multiple AI/ML, Data, Backend and devOPS engineers.
- Migrated monolithic backend application into 15 independent services
- o Introduced Golang & AWS Keyspaces/Cassandra, DynamoDB for high-load group chat application storage
- Promoted AWS Best Practices, executed AWS Well-Architected framework together with AWS solution architects
- Managed >40 EC2 servers across 3 AWS regions, migrated from AWS EC2 Classic to AWS VPC
- Updated codebase from PHP5 to PHP 7.4, Go 1.14 Docker 19, PHPUnit 9
- Supervised development of serverless microservices in Java/Kotlin/Golang & DynamoDB
- Split monorepository into >30 separate repositories with separate CI/CD
- Executed multiple refactoring projects in code, infrastructure, raw storage and databases
- Maintained backend roadmap and technology radar tech-radar.opensource.tandem.net based on ThoughtWorks
- Improved user retention analytics, subscriptions and overall revenue tracking
- Updated realtime messaging server RabbitMQ, secured authorization, added 3rd websocket/MQTT browser client
- Added support for in-app purchase gifting, subscription hold, grace periods, geo-search.
- o Increased application infrastructure and performance/APM monitoring automation and alerting via NewRelic
- Built full CI/CD pipeline on AWS Pipeline inc. Blue/Green deployments and AWS ASG/AutoScaling
- o Improved China & SEA connectivity via transparent HAProxy, ICP/Hosting issues resolved
- o Built internal business KPI, retention, engagement and revenue tracking systems
- Enforced PHPUnit & integration testing, code reviews & code style policies
- o Migrated application services into containers (Docker)

Senior FullStack Software Developer at Tandem Language Exchange App www.tandem.net,

Jun, 2013 - Jun, 2016 **③** 3 years

Mature backend solutions for audio/video (tele)communications software. Developed public API for mobile clients.

- Implemented public API for native mobile clients
- Refactored old MVP prototype codebase
- Launched first production release 1.0
- Celebrated first 50 users sign-up on GA and first promotions on iTunes
- o Deprecated legacy on-premise hosting and migrated into AWS EC2-Classic
- Celebrated '2015 Most innovative app of the year' award (Apple iTunes)
- Implemented PHP framework with open-source components
- Reduced API response times from >=2000ms to ~100ms
- Implemented critical app functionality: in-app messenger, real-time chat, community live feed, emailreminders, user search and more

Lead Software Developer at Yangutu LLC meetville.com,

Nov, 2011 - Nov, 2012 **③** 1 year

Working on web based social network.

- Added API for supporting external 3rd party Game-platform add-on's
- Added AMF Flex/ActionScript API Server for import/export of data to mobile platform
- Added Facebook, Instagram, VK and other social networks integrations
- Extended user data import and export API's

Software Engineer at eHarmony Inc www.eharmony.com,

Aug, 2008 - Sep, 2011 3 years 1 month

eHarmony Reporting and Management Tools for Risk Management team.

- Developed CMS/RMS Internal service from specification to manage and automate risks and fraud detection
- Working with sensitive client payment information
- Extended CMS/RMS service with flexible and configurable multi-role authentication system for different regions

- Added support for localization and translation of CMS/RMS
- Added analytics and audit tools for tracking and optimizing team (users or the CMS/RMS) performance

Software Engineer at IponWeb www.iponweb.com,

Aug, 2007 - Sep, 2011 **3** 4 years 1 month

SOAP/Rest API for real-time AD Exchange platform - RightMedia

- Worked on SOAP-API for high-load real-time advertising platform at scale
- Heavily extended and rewrote existing funtional test coverage, integrational e2e testing
- Covered many new edge cases in tests which lead to fixes in critical API parts

Software Engineer at Yahoo! yahoo.com,

May, 2008 - Mar, 2009 **①** 10 months

AD Exchange API - RightMedia

 Refactoring tests, code and documentation, working with remote Yahoo developers team. SOAP API. Perl. PHP5



#### **SKILLS**







# Leadership, SDM, SDLC





## **EDUCATION**

Experimental psychology, MSc Psychologe Pädagoge, Grodnenski Dzjaržauny Universitet Sep, 2005 - Sep, 2010

Elektrische Energietechnik (Power engineering), Electrical Engineering, GGPEK Elektrotechnik College Sep, 2000 - Sep, 2005



## **AWARDS**

## Ultimate Go , Certificate #1latfj6ukq

Awarded on: Jan 25, 2023

## AWS Certified Solutions Architect - Associate (SAA), Certificate #3GV5K7KKC14Q17W1

Awarded on: Dec 13, 2018

# AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner, Certificate #3B28554BK2EQ1PSD

Awarded on: Nov 21, 2020

## Telc Deutsch B1 Zertifikat, Certificate #0503718

Awarded on: May 01, 2018

